<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The epigrams of P. Virgilius Maro, and others With the praises of him and his workes. Also his epitaphs composed by diuers illustrious persons. And lastly, the arguments of his workes. Englished by I.P. louer of learning.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14502</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24825</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119271</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854478</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854478</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14502)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1044:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The epigrams of P. Virgilius Maro, and others With the praises of him and his workes. Also his epitaphs composed by diuers illustrious persons. And lastly, the arguments of his workes. Englished by I.P. louer of learning.</title>
                  <author>Penkethman, John.</author>
                  <author>Virgil, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[66] p. : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G[eorge] P[urslowe],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Ostensibly a translation of the Appendix Vergiliana with additions, but in fact no connection with the Appendix can be discerned. Only parts of the Appendix are attributed to Virgil.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Iohn Penkethman.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B (B5 + chi¹) C-D.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The epigrams of Virgil, and others.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Lacking inserted leaf after B5.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Virgil --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19902:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a man</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19902:1"/>
            <p>THE EPIGRAMS OF P. VIRGILIVS MARO, and others.</p>
            <p>WITH The Praiſes of him and his Workes.</p>
            <p>ALSO His Epitaphs compoſed by diuers illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And laſtly,</hi> the Arguments of his Workes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Engliſhed by</hi> I. P. <hi>louer of Learning.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Candidus à ſalibus ſuffuſis felle refugi:</l>
               <l>Nulla venenato littera miſta ioco eſt.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ouid. 2. Triſt.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>G.P.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19902:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19902:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST Flouriſhing and hopefull BRANCH of a moſt ancient and generous Stocke, NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THANIEL GVRLIN, of the honourable Society of Lincolnes Inne <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis Dedicatory cuſtome (as <hi>Lactantius</hi> teſtifies) hath beene ſince the time of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> and as I conceiue) will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue during the time of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> that <hi>is,</hi> the Planet ſo called, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for that a booke ſet forth
<pb facs="tcp:19902:3"/>without a Dedication, doth inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate or raiſe a ſuſpition in the Reader, that the Author ſtudies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute (as one vnworhy of a <hi>Mecoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas.</hi> For which cauſe, when I had finiſhed this Tranſlation accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my ſlender skill and weak wit, whereof I may ſay with <hi>Ouid,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Ingenium fregêre meum mala, cuius &amp; ante,</l>
                  <l>Fons infecundus, paruaque vena fuit.</l>
               </q> Muſing with my ſelfe, to whoſe Patronage I might eſpecially commend it, your noble worth worthy Sir, which way ſo ſoeuer I turn'd me, did ſtill preſent it ſelfe to my vnſetled mind, conſidering
<pb facs="tcp:19902:3"/>the generall fame of your pious inclination to vertue and good diſcipline (both which are copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly taught and expreſt in theſe Epigrams) with deteſtation of the contrary. Yet (worthy Sir) more exactly weighing that Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble courſe of life, wherin your ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led induſtry (by no vicious exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize interrupted) hath proued ſo proficient, that diuers yeeres ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence you haue meritoriouſly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Worſhipfull degree of Barriſter (which is rare in a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo youthfull) and are growne old in wiſdome, learning, and experience, I conceiued this pety Paper-preſent, as well for the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of its ſubiect from the
<pb facs="tcp:19902:4"/>matter of your practice, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of my rude workemanſhip hereupon beſtowed, to be farre be-beneath and come ſhort of your illuſtrious merit. Howbeit <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaies, it was vſuall with Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to make ſupplication vnto the Gods with Milke, and when they wanted Frankincenſe, to ſacrifice with a Cake made of meale, water, and ſalt, which (as hee thought) was no leſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted then the moſt coſtly and odoriferous burnt-offerings.</p>
            <p>Let therefore (worthy Sir) your nobly-diſpoſed hart with a cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full benignitie, entertaine this gratefull and zealous oblation, how meane and vnmeet ſoeuer it
<pb facs="tcp:19902:4"/>is, from the hands of him that will not only pray for your health and proſperous proceedings, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to deſerue your fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble regard by all reſpectiue ſeruice in his power, and approue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A moſt dutiful declarer of your Honour-worthy Vertues, <hi>Iohn Penkethman.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19902:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19902:5"/>
            <head>Vpon my worthy Patrons Name, NATHANIEL.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> (<hi>Scripture</hi> teſtifies)</l>
               <l>was named ſo, becauſe <hi>of God ordain'd;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or <hi>asked</hi> by his mother, in whoſe eies</l>
               <l>(as to her heart) moſt precious he remain'd,</l>
               <l>And ſtood in generall (as the ſacred Pen</l>
               <l>Records him) fauour'd both of God and men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So is <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> by Interpretation,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The gift of God;</hi> who gain'd the bleſsed iſtle,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Ieſus</hi> (as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> makes declaration)</l>
               <l>of a true <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> and void of guile;</l>
               <l>Whom, like a perfect <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> he confeſt</l>
               <l>To be <hi>God's</hi> Sonne, and King of Iſrael bleſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now, though but one of thoſe two happy Names</l>
               <l>to this my worthy Patron be aſsign'd;</l>
               <l>Loe, in his Perſon (as his life proclames)</l>
               <l>moſt gracious gifts of either be combin'd;</l>
               <l>Fabour'd of <hi>God</hi> and men, as by him ſent,</l>
               <l>And to his Mothers heart a ſweet content;</l>
               <l>A <hi>Chriſtian</hi> true, a <hi>Lawyer</hi> wanting fraud,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Wiſdome, Learning, vertues all applaud.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19902:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19902:6"/>
            <head>The Tranſlator to the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous-minded Engliſh Scholler, and the indifferent READER.</head>
            <p>MY Muſe being not inclined (according to the cuſtome of theſe times) to the inuention of ſcandalous or reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue Inuectiues, by way of Epigram or Satyre, either for the diſgorging of my ſtomake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any, (though occaſion doth excite mee to reproue many from whom I haue receiued inſufferable iniuries) or otherwiſe to carpe at the notorious humours and vices of particular perſons that neuer offended me, onely for oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation of my wit; but rather deſirous to ſpend my vacant houres, and imploy the poore portion of my little learning, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally for the good admonition and reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vicious, and inſtruction of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant,
<pb facs="tcp:19902:7"/>I haue aduentured (as formerly of the Schoole-book inſcribed with the name of <hi>Cato</hi>) to make interpretation of theſe Epigrams, which (notwithſtanding they were for the moſt part, the fruits of <hi>Virgils</hi> minority, being by him compoſed at his age of 15. yeeres, as I note in his life written by <hi>Donatus</hi>) doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuch variety of good doctrine, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite inuentions, that to me they ſeeme ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue beene brought forth in his Maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, when Learning, Iudgement and Wit in him were moſt mature, or elſe the greateſt number of them to haue iſſued (as <hi>Scaliger</hi> and other Commentors conceiue) from the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned heads of more ancient Poets. And for that cauſe I haue punctually obſerued the peculiar titles of theſe Epigrams as they ſtand in the laſt edition of the Latine, without addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or alteration of any Authors name, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering withall, that to know the workeman is not ſo materiall, or ſo much to be inquired and regarded, as the benefit and good vſe of the worke it ſelfe: and as in meates the wholſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is more to be wiſhed then the toothſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo in bookes, the goodneſſe of the matter is to bee preferred before the eloquence of the phraſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>But here ſome ſelfe-conceited <hi>Grammari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> being conditioned like the dog in the manger, neither willing to beſtow their owne ſtudies in tranſlating ſuch worke, nor permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting others, without a ſnarling reproofe, to performe that part, will peraduenture tax and accuſe me (as they haue done) of doing iniury to Learning, by making it ſo common, that now adaies they can diſcourſe or deliuer nothing of worth out of Latine Writers, but the Hearer (though the Latiniſt) is ready to take the tale by the end, as one that knowes already no leſſe then themſelues, and that Learning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is vilified, and daily groweth out of requeſt with many, who when their ſonnes haue ſpent ſome time at Schoole, to keepe them out of the durt (as they ſay) and from hurt and idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, chooſe rather to binde them Apprentice to deceitfull trades, and mechanike handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts, then to place them in the Vniuerſity, where with their yeeres they might increaſe in diſcipline, and conſequently become good members of the Church or Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>To theſe, I anſwer, that not onely in mine owne opinion, but by the approbation of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall (and thoſe profound) Schollers, whoſe workes extant doe witneſſe it, this cuſtome of
<pb facs="tcp:19902:8"/>tranſlating doth rather Right then Wrong to Learning. For the knowledge of good diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline ought not to be kept priuate or reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, like treaſure in a miſers cheſt, in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a few, but like the element of water, ſhould be publike and vſefull for all men. And Parents by this meanes of tranſlating, finding what excellent matters are comprized in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Authors, doe admire and fall in loue (as I may ſay) with the worth of Learning, and thereupon doe ſeeke to furniſh their children with what they ſee wanting in themſelues, hoping that the like fruit may be produced by their future ſtudies, and that at length the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers obſcure family may (as hath beene lately knowne, and ſome Latine Authors teſtifie) be ennobled by their ſonnes aduancement. And thus hauing briefly and plainely, forthe better vnderſtanding of the vnlearned, yet I hope ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently apologized for this my tranſlation, I leaue you to peruſe it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19902:8"/>
            <head>The Contents of this TRANSLATION.</head>
            <list>
               <head>Epigrams.</head>
               <item>THe praiſe of the Garden. <hi>Epig. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Wine and Women. <hi>Epig. 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Enuie. <hi>Epig. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Syrens charmes. <hi>Epig. 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the birth day of <hi>Aſmenus. Epig. 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Orpheus. Epig. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of gaming. <hi>Epig. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the letter <hi>Y. Epig. 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the <hi>12.</hi> labours of <hi>Hercules. Epig. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the ſame Labours. <hi>Epig. 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of theſe words, <hi>'Tis</hi> and <hi>Not. Epig. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of a good man. <hi>Epig. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the ages of diners liuing creatures. <hi>Epig. 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Muſes inuentions. <hi>Epig. 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of our Image in the water. <hi>Epig. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of a Riuer frozen. <hi>Epig. 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Iris,</hi> or the Rainbow. <hi>Epig. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:9"/>Of the riſing of the Sunne. <hi>Epig. 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the <hi>12.</hi> celeſtiall Signes. <hi>Epig. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the foure ſeaſons of the yeere. <hi>Epig. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In honour of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar. Epig. 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vpon the ſame <hi>Auguſtus. Epig. 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vpon <hi>Baliſta,</hi> a Schoole-maſter. <hi>Epig. 23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vpon a beautious Boy. <hi>Epig. 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Crow on <hi>Tarpeius. Epig. 25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Letters. <hi>Epig. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vpon the death of three. <hi>Epig. 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Fortune. <hi>Epig. 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of loue to <hi>Theotimus. Epig. 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Roſcius</hi> his beauty. <hi>Epig. 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To <hi>Phileros</hi> of loues power. <hi>Epig. 31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To <hi>Pamphila</hi> of an amorous extaſie. <hi>Epig. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To Shepheards of loues fire. <hi>Epig. 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a Thracian Boy. <hi>Epig. 34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Tombe of <hi>Lucrece. Epig. 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon <hi>Narciſſus. Epig. 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon <hi>3.</hi> Shepheards. <hi>Epig. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vpon <hi>3.</hi> Amazons fight. <hi>Epig. 38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of an Hermaphrodite. <hi>Epig. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Acis</hi> a beautifull Boy. <hi>Epig. 40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Tombe of <hi>Hector. Epig. 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Tombe of <hi>Achilles. Epig. 42</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:9"/>
               <head>The ſeuerall Praiſes of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil and his workes.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Virgil</hi> of himſelfe. <hi>Epig. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Virgil. Epig. 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Virgils</hi> Aeneid. <hi>Epig. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Caeſars</hi> edict for the preſeruation of the Aeneid. <hi>Epig. 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Virgils</hi> Aeneid preſerued. <hi>Epig. 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In praiſe of the Aeneid. <hi>Epig. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Virgils</hi> wanton writing. <hi>Epig. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Virgil. Epig. 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon <hi>Virgil,</hi> and his workes. <hi>Epig. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon his Georgicks. <hi>Epig. 10</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>The Epitaps vpon <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Owens <hi>Epitaph.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Arguments of his Workes, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Monoſticks of</hi> all his workes. <hi>Epig. 1</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tetraſtichs of</hi> his <hi>Georgicks. Epig. 2</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Monoſtichs of</hi> his <hi>Aeneids. Epig. 3</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Penteſtichs of</hi> the ſame with the Supply by <hi>Mapheus. Epig. 4</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Decaſtichs of</hi> the ſame. <hi>Epig. 5</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="epigrams">
            <pb facs="tcp:19902:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19902:10"/>
            <head>THE EPIGRAMS <hi>of</hi> VIRGIL, and others.</head>
            <div n="1" type="epigram">
               <head>The praiſe of the Garden.</head>
               <l>FRom greateſt <hi>Ioue,</hi> ye Muſes that doe ſpring,</l>
               <l>The Gardens praiſe, come helpe me all to ſing,</l>
               <l>With wholſome food the hungry fleſh it fils,</l>
               <l>And diuers fruits affords to him that tils:</l>
               <l>Sweet Pot-herbs, and of many kinds more deare,</l>
               <l>Delicious Grapes, and what the Trees doe beare:</l>
               <l>Nor does the Garden ſpeciall pleaſures want;</l>
               <l>But thoſe it hath, with profits nothing ſcant;</l>
               <l>The murmuring glaſſie Brooke the ſame beſets,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Seeds the furrow-guided water wets:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:11"/>With diuers-colour'd buds gay flowers abound,</l>
               <l>With gemmy glories garniſhing the ground;</l>
               <l>The gainefull Bees with gentle noiſe doe hum,</l>
               <l>Flowers tops or new dews gathering where they come;</l>
               <l>The fertile Vine, th'Elme her Yoke-fellow lades,</l>
               <l>And with her Branches th'others wouen ſhades,</l>
               <l>Faire-ſhady-ſheltring Bowers the Trees doe yeeld vs,</l>
               <l>And their thicke boughs from <hi>Phoebus</hi> parching ſhield vs,</l>
               <l>Sweet ſounds, the pratling Birds abroad doe ſend,</l>
               <l>Their Songs, our Eares, alluring to attend;</l>
               <l>The Garden doth excite, deteine, feed, pleaſe,</l>
               <l>And our ſad minds of heauy ſorrowes eaſe,</l>
               <l>Brings vigour to our bodies, cheeres our ſight,</l>
               <l>With fuller fauours doth our paines requite,</l>
               <l>And giues the trimmer manifold delight.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Of Wine and Women.</head>
               <l>LEt not the loue of wine or women ſeize thee,</l>
               <l>For wine and women both alike diſeaſe thee:</l>
               <l>As <hi>Venus</hi> mars the ſtrength, ſo <hi>Bacchus</hi> flowing,</l>
               <l>Workes weakneſſe in our feet, and trips our Going.</l>
               <l>Many, their ſecrets through blinde Loue detect,</l>
               <l>And Drunkenneſſe doth worke the like effect,</l>
               <l>Fierce loue is often cauſe of deadly war,</l>
               <l>So copious Cups not ſeldome make vs iar.</l>
               <l>With fearefull fight, vile <hi>Venus</hi> waſted Troy,</l>
               <l>So <hi>Bacchus,</hi> thou the Lapithes didſt deſtroy:</l>
               <l>In ſhort, when either doth mans minde poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>He's void of goodneſſe, feare, and ſhamefaſtneſſe.</l>
               <l>In bonds <hi>Lyaeus,</hi> fettring <hi>Venus,</hi> binde,</l>
               <l>Leaſt thou, i'th gifts of either damage finde:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:11"/>Wine ſlakes our thirſt, Luſt for creation ſerues,</l>
               <l>Beyond theſe bounds he ſuffers harme that ſwerues.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Of Enuie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ENuy, a poiſon of corrupting power,</l>
                  <l>In wicked men (whoſe boſomes it conteine)</l>
                  <l>The bones vntouch't, the marrow doth deuoure,</l>
                  <l>And drinkes vp all their bloud through euery veine;</l>
                  <l>For he that doth anothers Fortune ſpight,</l>
                  <l>Becomes his owne Tormenter, as by right.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His heauy griefes, with Groanes he doth vnfold:</l>
                  <l>He ſighs, he frets, his Teeth together hits;</l>
                  <l>Beholding what he hates, he ſweats with cold,</l>
                  <l>And from his euill mouth, blacke venim ſpits,</l>
                  <l>His eie-lids a pale fearefull colour takes,</l>
                  <l>And bare his Bones vnhappy leanneſſe makes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To him, nor light, nor diet ſeemeth ſweet,</l>
                  <l>No drinke delights him, nor the taſte of Wine,</l>
                  <l>Though <hi>Ioue</hi> himſelfe ſhould deigne his lips to greet,</l>
                  <l>With propination from his cup diuine.</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Hebe</hi> reach and ſerue the ſame vnto him,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Ganimede</hi> with profer'd Nectar wooe him.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He neuer ſleepe enioyes, or boſome-peace,</l>
                  <l>That bloudy Torturer his bowels vexeth,</l>
                  <l>And mouing ſecret furies doth increaſe,</l>
                  <l>Flames of <hi>Erynnis</hi> that his heart perplexeth,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Titius</hi>-like, within him he doth finde,</l>
                  <l>A vulture that doth rend and eat his minde.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19902:12"/>Cloſe in his pining breaſt doth liue a wound,</l>
                  <l>Which not the hand of <hi>Chiron</hi> can make ſound:</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Phoebus,</hi> or his Ofſpring moſt renownd.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>4</hi> Of the Syrens charmes.</head>
               <l>VArietie of Songs and Heauy notes</l>
               <l>Were wont to iſſue from the Syrens throtes:</l>
               <l>Their voyces and their warbling Muſe did moue,</l>
               <l>All tunes that pleaſant <hi>Thymele</hi> did loue:</l>
               <l>That which the Trumpet and hoarſe Horne laments,</l>
               <l>That which the Pipe ſounds with a thouſand vents:</l>
               <l>What the light Reeds, or what ſweet <hi>Aedon</hi> can,</l>
               <l>What the Harpe yeeldeth, or the dying Swan:</l>
               <l>Shipmen with meaſures muſicall prouokde,</l>
               <l>In flouds <hi>Ionian</hi> they haue often chokde.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> great from <hi>Siſiphus</hi> deſcended</l>
               <l>Safely, by this Art onely, his defended:</l>
               <l>Subtly with wax his fellowes eares he ſhut,</l>
               <l>And his owne hands in manicles he put;</l>
               <l>The Rocks and dangerous ſhores his nauy paſt,</l>
               <l>And in the Sea themſelues the Syrens caſt.</l>
               <l>Thus flattring Notes and Songs he ouer went,</l>
               <l>And rauiſhing Monſters into ruine ſent.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>5</hi> Of the birth day of <hi>Aſmenus.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>TItan</hi> come forth with vnoffended light,</l>
               <l>And cheerfull Morne greet all with heauen bright.</l>
               <l>You young men alſo, kinde in heart and voice,</l>
               <l>With happy vowes this Holy day reioyce.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:12"/>That it returning proſperous euery yeare,</l>
               <l>His children, gifts to him with ioy may beare.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="epigram">
               <head>6 <hi>Of</hi> Orpheus.</head>
               <l>THe <hi>Thracian</hi> Poet with ſweet Harpe is thought</l>
               <l>In ſauage Beaſts, milde motions to haue wrought,</l>
               <l>And ſtayd the waters, as they paſt along,</l>
               <l>The ſenſleſſe Rockes alluring with a ſong,</l>
               <l>And Trees attending ſuch ſweet-ſounding Layes,</l>
               <l>Him, as they ſay, one ſhadow'd in his wayes:</l>
               <l>Yea more, he made, by pleaſing ſpeeches, milde,</l>
               <l>And ciuill, by lips learned, people wilde:</l>
               <l>To one Societie this <hi>Orpheus</hi> brought them,</l>
               <l>Poliſht their Manners rude, and Iuſtice taught them.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>7</hi> Of Gaming.</head>
               <l>HAte Lucre, mad Deſire doth deeply grieue:</l>
               <l>Old men flie Fraud; vnskill'd, the skill'd beleeue.</l>
               <l>Gameſters, their mindes muſt with their money lay:</l>
               <l>Shun ſpightfull Strife, when thou art queld in play:</l>
               <l>Play ye ſecure that ſtill haue coyne in ſtore:</l>
               <l>Who comes in monyed, ſo departs no more.</l>
               <l>Couetous Gameſters goe by weeping Croſſe:</l>
               <l>Good men loue peace; leaue Anger, hauing loſſe,</l>
               <l>No man in Game can euer luckie bee;</l>
               <l>Wrath make the Furies, Foure, at firſt but Three.</l>
               <l>Chaſtiſe thy raging ſpirits, true to play:</l>
               <l>Timely fly fighting, and put Ire away.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="epigram">
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>8</hi> Of the Letter y.</head>
               <l>THis Two-horn'd letter of <hi>Pythagoras</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Seemes to do denote, how Men their liues doe paſſe:</l>
               <l>Steepe on the Right hand, Vertues way is bent,</l>
               <l>Which at firſt ſight hard entrance doth preſent,</l>
               <l>Yet giues the wearied Reſt, when they attaine</l>
               <l>The higheſt Top: the left way broad and plaine</l>
               <l>Shewes a ſoft iourney, but the bounds at laſt</l>
               <l>Captiu'd, by ſteepe Rockes, headlong all doe caſt:</l>
               <l>For whoſoere for Vertues loues endures,</l>
               <l>Both praiſe and honour to himſelfe procures:</l>
               <l>But he that artleſſe Luxury purſues,</l>
               <l>Or Sloth, and labour offerd doth refuſe</l>
               <l>With inconſiderate minde, his time ſhall ſpend</l>
               <l>In ſhame and want, and reape a wretched end.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>9</hi> Of the <hi>12.</hi> Labours of <hi>Hercules.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CLeone</hi> ſaw him firſt the Lion fell,</l>
               <l>Next <hi>Lerna</hi>'s ſerpent, Shaft and fire did quell.</l>
               <l>After with life th'<hi>Erymanthian</hi> Bore did part,</l>
               <l>Which done, of golden hornes he reft the Hart.</l>
               <l>Thoſe won, the Birds of <hi>Stymphalus</hi> he foild,</l>
               <l>Then th'Amazonian of her Belt he ſpoild.</l>
               <l>By ſeuenth toyle he purg'd a Stable full,</l>
               <l>By eighth, he triumpht in th'expulſed Bull.</l>
               <l>By ninth, both Horſe and Maſter he confounded,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Geryons</hi> end, <hi>Spaine</hi> his tenth glory ſounded.</l>
               <l>Apples of Gold were his eleuenth gaines,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Pluto</hi>'s Porter period of his paines.</l>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="epigram">
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>12</hi> A good Man.</head>
               <l>A Wiſe good man, (where wiſdomes God in many,</l>
               <l>Yea many thouſands hath found hardly any)</l>
               <l>Himſelfe doth cenſure and ſearch euery where,</l>
               <l>And what Repute with all ſorts he doth beare:</l>
               <l>Round, like the World, abiding, and ſecure,</l>
               <l>Leſt his plague Out-ſide blemiſh doe endure:</l>
               <l>He weighes in <hi>Cancer,</hi> when the day-light ends</l>
               <l>How farre the night in <hi>Capricorne</hi> extends.</l>
               <l>And with iuſt Ballance himſelfe poyſeth well,</l>
               <l>Leſt either Cleft appeare or Angle ſwell;</l>
               <l>That all his parts may equally befit,</l>
               <l>And that the Plumbe line may not ſwerue a whit,</l>
               <l>He muſt be ſollid all; no emptineſſe,</l>
               <l>Let erring fingers force in him expreſſe.</l>
               <l>Let not his Eye lids be to ſleepe inclinde,</l>
               <l>Ere he his daies whole actions call to minde;</l>
               <l>What he hath ſlipt, what done, in, out of ſeaſon;</l>
               <l>Why this fact wanted comelineſſe, that reaſon:</l>
               <l>What I haue paſt: why this opinion ſtood,</l>
               <l>Which for me to haue chang'd, it had beene good:</l>
               <l>Why pittying him that feels wants bitterſmart,</l>
               <l>I ſuffered Griefe with an effeminate heart.</l>
               <l>Why would what I ſhould not, and why gaine,</l>
               <l>Rather then goodneſſe did I entertaine.</l>
               <l>Whether in Speech or Lookes harſh any knew me;</l>
               <l>Why Nature more then Learnings vertue drew me:</l>
               <l>Thus paſſing through, what he hath ſayd and done;</l>
               <l>And, not long after Setting of the Sun,</l>
               <l>All things reuoluing, with the Bad offended,</l>
               <l>He giues the Palme to th'Good by him commended.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="epigram">
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>13</hi> Of the ages of diuers liuing</head>
               <l>creatures.</l>
               <l>THe life of Man moſt commonly outweares,</l>
               <l>Being complete, foureſcore and ſixteene yeares:</l>
               <l>And theſe, nine times exceeds the pratling Crow;</l>
               <l>Yet doth the Hart that age foure times o're goe:</l>
               <l>And thrice his yeeres expirde, the Rauen dies:</l>
               <l>But thoſe, the Phoenix nine times multiplies:</l>
               <l>Yet th'Hamadriades Nymphs, paſt compare,</l>
               <l>Breathe nine times longer then that Bird ſo rare.</l>
               <l>Thoſe creatures vitall fates theſe bounds reſtraining,</l>
               <l>The reſt God knowes, the ſecret Age ordaining.</l>
               <lg>
                  <head>Some men ſet before them theſe two others.</head>
                  <l>AHedge three yeeres, a Dog, three hedges courſes:</l>
                  <l>A Horſe, three Dogs; a Man out-liues three Horſes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>14</hi> Of the Muſes inuentions.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CLio</hi> things done doth afterwards reherſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Melpomene</hi> ſhewes all in Tragicke verſe.</l>
               <l>To wanton words her minde <hi>Thalia</hi> bends,</l>
               <l>Sweet ſounds from hollow reeds <hi>Euterpe</hi> ſends.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Terpſichore,</hi> loue with Harpe moues, rules, augments.</l>
               <l>With ſongs, lookes, dances, <hi>Erato</hi> contents.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:14"/>
                  <hi>Calliope</hi> indites heroicke lines.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vrania</hi> notes heauens motions, ſtarres and ſignes.</l>
               <l>Speaking with geſture <hi>Polymneia</hi> ſtands,</l>
               <l>And figures all things with her learned hands.</l>
               <l>Theſe on all parts <hi>Apollo</hi>'s vertue guides,</l>
               <l>And he ith'midſt, embracing all, abides.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="epigram">
               <head>Of the ſame in proſe.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Clio</hi> inuented Hiſtories.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Melpomene</hi> inuented Tragedies</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thalia</hi> inuented Comedies.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Euterpe</hi> inuented Flutes and ſuch like.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Terpſichore</hi> inuented The Harpe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Erato</hi> inuented Geometrie.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Calliope</hi> inuented Letters.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vrania</hi> inuented Aſtrologie.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Polymneia.</hi> inuented Rhetoricke.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>15</hi> Of our Image in the water.</head>
               <head>Diſtichs varied <hi>12.</hi> ſeuerall wayes.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>THe looker ſees his lookes in water cleare,</l>
                  <l>As in an obiect-myrror they appeare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>Pure formes from water to the ſight doe paſſe,</l>
                  <l>As from the ſplendour of a looking glaſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>The fountaine repreſents our likeneſſe right,</l>
                  <l>Such as the ſteele-glaſſe, which is plaine and bright.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:15"/>
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>Still Waters, figures oppoſite, no leſſe</l>
                  <l>Then myrrours through their brightneſſe, doe expreſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>Springs voyde of mud diſſemble our Aſpects,</l>
                  <l>As each bright myrrors orbe the ſame reflects.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>Cleare Water is the chryſtall mirrors ape,</l>
                  <l>For either to Spectators tels their ſhape.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>Fountaines moſt cleare ſhew faces ſeeming true,</l>
                  <l>Like Glaſſe, that women, for their dreſſing, view.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>As the Beholders forme, Steele-glaſſes take,</l>
                  <l>So Formes their Image in the water make.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>Feign'd Shapes in Conduit-heads, the Right ingender,</l>
                  <l>As to each face, the Glaſſe a face doth render.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>The Spring vntroubled Shape for Shape doth yeeld,</l>
                  <l>As Subſtance, Shadowes in a Glaſſie field.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>Bodies in quiet Springs are ſeene againe:</l>
                  <l>As Images appeare in Mirrors plaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>The Viewer viewes himſelfe in glaſſie Brookes,</l>
                  <l>As in that brittle ſtuffe, whereon he lookes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>16</hi> Of a Riuer Frozen.</head>
               <head>Diſtichs varied <hi>12.</hi> ſeuerall wayes.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>WHere Ships did vſe to plow, yok'd Oxen drew,</l>
                  <l>When once hard Winter did the Waters glew.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:15"/>
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>The Floud beares Wheels, where Shipmen ſails did ſtrike</l>
                  <l>So ſoone as Froſt congeales it Marble-like.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>Hardned with Winters cold, the Waters bore</l>
                  <l>Waines drawne with Oxen, that Ships cut before.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>To ſolid Ice the Riuer being chang'd,</l>
                  <l>Indures the Wheele, where fleeting veſſels rang'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>The Carres, where Ships were wont, haue paſt the flood,</l>
                  <l>Since, turn'd to Ice, like Marble it hath ſtood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>A road for Carres, where Ships did run, is made,</l>
                  <l>With Froſt the Waters being firmly laid.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>In place of Ships the Trackt of Wheeles is found,</l>
                  <l>Since Icy Winter the looſe Waters bound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>Yok'd Oxen draw the Waine where Ships did reele,</l>
                  <l>Winds hauing hardned Waues to beare the Wheele.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>The Beaſt now drags where Mariners did ſound,</l>
                  <l>The Riuer being turn'd to maſſie ground.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>The Streame with cold extreme now firme abiding,</l>
                  <l>Beares vp the the Waine where Ships were lately riding.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>No ſooner be the Waues by <hi>Boreas</hi> quaild,</l>
                  <l>But we driue Oxen, where before we ſaild.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>By the Tranſlatour to make vp a dozen.</head>
                  <l>Now Carters play their parts where Saylers acted,</l>
                  <l>To a firme Stage, Froſt hauing Waues contracted.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="epigram">
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>17</hi> Of Iris or the Rainbow.</head>
               <head>Diſtichs varied <hi>12.</hi> ſeuerall wayes.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>IRis</hi> in diuers hues her ſelfe arrayes,</l>
                  <l>And flies with painted Bow through cloudy wayes,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Sol</hi> thereon hath caſt his burning rayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>When <hi>Phoebus</hi> fills the olouds with radiant light,</l>
                  <l>With diuers colours <hi>Iris</hi> comes in ſight,</l>
                  <l>Adorning heauen with her compaſſe bright.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>In clouds <hi>Thaumantias</hi> brightly ſhining raignes,</l>
                  <l>From whence a picturde vaile Heauens viſage gaines,</l>
                  <l>When once the Sunne a rainy ſhowre attaines.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>The hot Suns light wet clouds no ſooner weare,</l>
                  <l>But many-figur'd <hi>Iris</hi> doth appeare,</l>
                  <l>And therewith beautifies the welkin cleare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>While Sunne and ſhowrie clouds nought keeps aſunder,</l>
                  <l>The Raine doth ſundry figures forme thereunder,</l>
                  <l>Which we the Raine-bow call, and view with wonder.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>If to darke clouds the Sun his Beames obiect,</l>
                  <l>And to the ſhowre oppoſd their light reflect,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe clouds with colours are by <hi>Iris</hi> deckt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>The Raine-bow girts the clouds with wondrous Art,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Phoebus</hi> reaching on the aduerſe part,</l>
                  <l>Rare colours through the ſame doth ſubtly dart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:16"/>
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>Where <hi>Phoebus</hi> with his Beames moyſt clouds out-faceth,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iris,</hi> whom many a glorious colour graceth,</l>
                  <l>With comely Orbe the cloudy skie embraceth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>On watry clouds if <hi>Sol</hi> his luſtre throw,</l>
                  <l>Then does the liquid humour ſhine below,</l>
                  <l>And we behold a varie-figur'd Bow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>The gathering ſhowre diſſolu'd by <hi>Phoebus</hi> beames,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iris,</hi> ſo called in Greeke, thereunder ſtreames,</l>
                  <l>Decking heauens Cope with many-colour'd leames.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>Colour'd is <hi>Jris</hi> through light vnder laid,</l>
                  <l>Which of a ſhowry cloud the Sun hath made,</l>
                  <l>When with his Heate the Wet is ouer-ſwayd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>With light when <hi>Sol</hi> hath fill'd a rainy Cloud,</l>
                  <l>Straight <hi>Iris</hi> like a ſemi-circle, bow'd,</l>
                  <l>Shines forth with many-figur'd parts endow'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>18</hi> Of the riſing of the Sun.</head>
               <head>Tetraſtichs varied <hi>12.</hi> ſeuerall wayes.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>MOrne came from Sea, as vaild with Saffron bright,</l>
                  <l>And on her two-wheeld Chariot bluſhing ſat;</l>
                  <l>The candent Orbe the pole beſpred with light,</l>
                  <l>And ſhining with cleare beames vp <hi>Phoebus</hi> gat.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>Forth walks <hi>Aurora</hi> in a Roſie robe,</l>
                  <l>Dying with orient light the Starry round:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Sol</hi> from <hi>Tethis</hi> lap, this Earthly globe,</l>
                  <l>Comes to illumine with beames glory crown'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:17"/>
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>The golden Sun from th'Ocean raiſd his head,</l>
                  <l>And then through heauen the ſtars appeard no more:</l>
                  <l>With reuerence to his brightneſſe, darkneſſe fled,</l>
                  <l>And light to all things did their hue reſtore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>The Earth by <hi>Tithon</hi>'s ruddy-colourd ſpouſe,</l>
                  <l>With roſie light is dide, and ſtarry skie,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Phoebus,</hi> from the deepe his horſe doth rowze,</l>
                  <l>With firie wheeles, and makes the ſtarres to flie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>Night, whom a veile of ſtarres doth faire adorne,</l>
                  <l>Returnes amaine perceiuing day to riſe,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Phoebus</hi> in his golden chariot borne,</l>
                  <l>Makes all things here ſeeme glorious in our eyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>With roſie haire the golden Morne appeard,</l>
                  <l>And Earth was moiſtned with an early dew,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Sol</hi> himſelfe from <hi>Tethis</hi> boſome reard,</l>
                  <l>With flaming viſage, and eye-dazling hew.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Titan</hi> diſperſing ore Seas, Earth, and Aire,</l>
                  <l>His gliſtring light, now forth againe is ridden:</l>
                  <l>The Starres forbeare to ſhine with golden haire,</l>
                  <l>And ſable <hi>Nox</hi> her twinkling fires hath hidden.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sol</hi> with his luſtre from the Ocean-ſtreames,</l>
                  <l>Rearing his chariot, hath reſtor'd the day,</l>
                  <l>And, by reducing his flammigerous beames,</l>
                  <l>To heauen and earth, hath driuen the ſtar resaway.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>The Skie faire <hi>Memnons</hi> mother hauing dide,</l>
                  <l>And with her roſie hands the Starres exilde,</l>
                  <l>Now from the Sea <hi>Latona</hi>'s ſonne is hy'd,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Orbe the day and aire hath reconcilde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:17"/>
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>Bluſhing <hi>Aurora</hi> vſher'd <hi>Phoebus</hi> Carre,</l>
                  <l>And he his Courſers from the Ocean brought,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe rayes de pelling each night-wandring Starre,</l>
                  <l>Dayes reſtitution to all mankinde wrought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>Dayes charriot ſcarce had made the Welkin red,</l>
                  <l>And new dewes topt the flowers, herbs, and weeds,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Phoebus</hi> left his louers watry bed,</l>
                  <l>And Starres gaue place to his flame-bearing ſteeds.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Titans</hi> faire daughter with Ambroſian weed,</l>
                  <l>Her white feet ſhadowes, from the Sea aſcended;</l>
                  <l>Then with bright beames her Father doth proceed,</l>
                  <l>Thence driuing darkneſſe, and Nights rule is ended.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>19</hi> Of the twelue celeſtiall Signes.</head>
               <head>Hexaſtichs varied <hi>12.</hi> ſeuerall wayes.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>THe Ram, the Bull with golden-horned head,</l>
                  <l>The Brethren, and the Crabfiſh backwards tending.</l>
                  <l>The Lion fierce, the Maid that did not wed,</l>
                  <l>The Scales, the Scorpion with her taile offending,</l>
                  <l>The Shooter, and the Goat with horny ſute,</l>
                  <l>The Water-powrer, and the Fiſhes mute.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>Who <hi>Helle,</hi> who <hi>Europa</hi> carried ſoly,</l>
                  <l>The Twins, the Shelfiſh, that <hi>Alcides</hi> quaſht,</l>
                  <l>The horrid king of Beaſts, the Virgin holy,</l>
                  <l>The Ballance iuſt, with Taile what deadly laſht,</l>
                  <l>Old <hi>Chiron, Capricorne,</hi> the Lad, like raine,</l>
                  <l>Miniſtring Water, and the Fiſhes twaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:18"/>
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>The firſt is <hi>Aries;</hi> next is <hi>Taurus</hi> plac't;</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Gemini; Cancer</hi> followes retrograde;</l>
                  <l>The fifth is <hi>Leo;</hi> the ſixth <hi>Virgo</hi> chaſt;</l>
                  <l>And after <hi>Libra, Scorpius</hi> doth inuade;</l>
                  <l>Yet <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> and <hi>Caper</hi> paſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aquarius</hi> comes, and <hi>Piſces</hi> at the laſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>The chiefe all Ram-kinde, the Cowes mate ſucceeds,</l>
                  <l>Two of one birth be third, the fourth Crabs feature:</l>
                  <l>Lord of the Deſart, ſhe that neuer breeds,</l>
                  <l>The poizer of all weights, the ſtinging creature,</l>
                  <l>The Bow-arm'd Centaure, the Venerious beaſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioues</hi> water-bearer, and the Friday-feaſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>The crooked Ram-hornes, the Bulls threatning hookes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Leda</hi>'s male iſſue, the Fiſh hotneſſe bringing,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Hercules</hi> firſt prize, the beauteous lookes,</l>
                  <l>The Weighing meaſure, and the Serpent ſtinging,</l>
                  <l>The skilfull Archer, and the Winter ſigne,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Troian</hi> boy, the Fiſhes laſtly ſhine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Phryxus</hi> tranſporter, <hi>Ioue</hi> with hornes diſguiſde,</l>
                  <l>His Twin-borne ſonnes, the Crawler tropica! I,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Nemean</hi> terrour, Maid immortalizde:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sol</hi>'s Weigh-houſe, and whoſe Pricke inuenoms all,</l>
                  <l>The Man halfe-Horſe, the Starre with taile of fiſh,</l>
                  <l>The Water-titled, and the Anglers diſh.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>The lecherous Weather, and th' vngelded Oxe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> and the Starre aduſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nemea</hi>'s plague, Maids face, of <hi>Lux</hi> with <hi>Nox,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Th' <hi>Autumnian</hi> equallizer, poyſning Thruſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Phillyra</hi>'s monſtrous birth, cauſe of Sea-ſtormes,</l>
                  <l>The Riuer-giuer, and the Fiſhy formes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:18"/>
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>The flocks wooll-bearing Head, the Heifer ſtout,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tyndaridae, Alcides</hi> crawling foe,</l>
                  <l>Chiefe of wild Creatures, Virgin moſt deuout,</l>
                  <l>The pendent paire, the Venomous piercing blow,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saturnes</hi> baſe iſſue, the Goate <hi>Neptune</hi>-growne,</l>
                  <l>Faire <hi>Ganymed,</hi> two fiſhy Signes in one.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>The Rams proportion, and the Bull vnbaited,</l>
                  <l>The double Ofſpring, the Sea-foſtred Crab,</l>
                  <l>The Lions lookes, <hi>Erygone</hi> tranſlated,</l>
                  <l>The poyzing Yoke, the Taile with poyſning ſtab,</l>
                  <l>Biformed <hi>Chiron,</hi> the Seas Horned creature,</l>
                  <l>The chiefe Gods minion, and the Fiſhes feature.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>The flocks horn'd Guide, another arm'd with horne,</l>
                  <l>The Swan got ſonnes, the Crabs hot-burning armes,</l>
                  <l>The club-feld Horrour, the Maid bringing corne,</l>
                  <l>Meanes of true Meaſure, cauſe of Poyſnous harmes,</l>
                  <l>The wood-bred Archer, <hi>Iupiters</hi> milker-giuer,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deucalions</hi> waters, and two bred ith' Riuer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>Sire of the Sheepe, <hi>Europa</hi>'s worſt well-willer,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Zetus</hi> and ſweet <hi>Amphion,</hi> Summer-bringer,</l>
                  <l>That ſeaſons ſecond ſigne, the Maid ſelfe-killer,</l>
                  <l>The Harueſt-entring ſtarre, the Mortall ſtinger,</l>
                  <l>The Shaft ſore-wounded Huntſman, the Sea-goate,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioues</hi> fauourite, and ſuch as liue ith' Mote.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>By the Tranſlatour, to make them euen.</head>
                  <l>The Signe ith' head, what alteration puts</l>
                  <l>Ith' necke, Armes-guider, keeper of the Breſt,</l>
                  <l>Our hearts Free-holder, Lady of the Guts,</l>
                  <l>Reines-ruler, where the Secrets are poſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19902:19"/>The Gouernour of Thighes, Knees' Conſtellation.</l>
                  <l>Lord of the Legs, cauſe of the feets mutation.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>20</hi> The <hi>4.</hi> ſeaſons of the yeere.</head>
               <head>Tetraſtichs varied <hi>13.</hi> ſeuerall wayes.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>EArth opes her wombe ith' Spring, and giues vs Flowers</l>
                  <l>The fat field beares rich Eares in Sunny howers.</l>
                  <l>The Grapes abounding Autumne brings to tunning,</l>
                  <l>And Winter binds in Ice the Waters running.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>The Spring, the cleare skie tempring, Froſt confounds,</l>
                  <l>But with <hi>Sols</hi> fires hot Summer chaps the grounds:</l>
                  <l>Weake Heat with Harueſt neighbouring Winter mixeth,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe the whitened Riuers hardly fixeth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ver</hi> paints the Meads with ſundry colours gay,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeſtas</hi> the ſoile with Corne-eares doth array:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Autumnus</hi> from the Vines their burden takes,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Hyems</hi> great with Snow the Welkin makes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> in Spring-time flowry garlands weares,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ceres</hi> in Summer chiefly domineeres:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bacchus</hi> in Harueſt beares a ſpeciall ſway,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Boreas</hi> in Winter doth the Ruffin play.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>Spring laſting, Herbes and Flowers <hi>Tellus</hi> yeelds,</l>
                  <l>Summer brings fruitfull Crops to harrowed fields:</l>
                  <l>Hatueſt from tender Vines affords vs fruite,</l>
                  <l>Winter in White the Earth doth coldly ſute.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:19"/>
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>New Spring the field with ſweet flowres doth adorne,</l>
                  <l>And plough-lands are made rough with Summer Corne,</l>
                  <l>Muſt foaming Veſſels doth in Autumne heate,</l>
                  <l>And Winter-blaſts from Trees the Leaues doe beate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>Wreathes knit of many a flowre the Spring allowes,</l>
                  <l>With ſheaues of Corne the Summer decks her browes:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bacchus</hi> in Autumne from the Vine is crown'd,</l>
                  <l>Sad Winter ſutes with Snow the mountaine-ground.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>The Spring with ſplendent flowres the fields makes faire,</l>
                  <l>Subſtance for Bread the Summer doth prepare:</l>
                  <l>Sweet ſmels the Vineyard with Autumn all birth,</l>
                  <l>But Winter freezes Flouds, robs Woods and Earth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>From Earth ſpring purple flowres ith' leauy Spring,</l>
                  <l>The fields in Summer gifts of <hi>Ceres</hi> bring,</l>
                  <l>In Harueſt howres our Cups with <hi>Bacchus</hi> flow,</l>
                  <l>Cold Winter Clothes our Mother Earth in ſnow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>Th' aire waxeth warm ith' Spring when Southwinds blow</l>
                  <l>Through heat Eſtiuall, Riuers leſſer grow,</l>
                  <l>Autumne, thy temper flowes with Nectar ſweet,</l>
                  <l>And ſhowres of Snow in Winter Earth doe greet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>Flowres grace the Spring, nought drooping while it laſts,</l>
                  <l>The fields with Corne abound through Summer blaſts,</l>
                  <l>The Vine to Elmes in Autumne loading cleaues,</l>
                  <l>Hyemall rage Woods of their glory reaues.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>Sweet Spring with flowers paints the graſſie way,</l>
                  <l>The ſith-arm'd Goddeſſe corne in Summer ſtayes:</l>
                  <l>Autumne for Muſt plumpe-ſwelling Grapes doth beare,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sythonian</hi> Snow makes Winter old appeare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:20"/>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3</head>
                  <l>The Spring ſtood freſh, girt with a flowry wreathe,</l>
                  <l>And Summer naked, a corne-crowne beneathe,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Autumne</hi> ſtood with Grapes in baskets preſt,</l>
                  <l>And Icy Winter rough with hoary creſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>21</hi> In honour of <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
               </head>
               <byline>By Virgil.</byline>
               <lg>
                  <l>ALL night it raines, ith'morne the Shewes appeare;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caeſar</hi> with <hi>Ioue</hi> diuided rule doth beare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>J theſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſes did compoſe,</l>
                  <l>But the praiſe another choſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So you, not for you, Birds knit ſlender peeces,</l>
                  <l>So you, not for you, Cattell weare your fleeces,</l>
                  <l>So you, not for you, Bees your Sweet prepare,</l>
                  <l>So you, not for you, Oxen draw the Share.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>22</hi> Vpon the ſame <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>IOue</hi> in Heauen gouernes all:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> on this Earthly Ball.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="epigram">
               <head>23 <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon</hi> Baliſta.</head>
               <l>THis Hill of Stones doth dead <hi>Baliſta</hi> hold:</l>
               <l>Both day and night now, Traueller, goe bold.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="epigram">
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>24</hi> Vpon a beauteous Boy.</head>
               <l>NAture, what ſex to giue thee, being in doubt,</l>
               <l>Of both well neere hath fram'd thee (faire) throughout</l>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>25</hi> Vpon the Crow on <hi>Tarpeius.</hi>
               </head>
               <byline>By an vncertaine Authour.</byline>
               <l>LOng ſince vpon Mount Tarpey ſat the Crow,</l>
               <l>She could not ſay, 'tis well, but ſhall be ſo.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>26</hi> Of Letters.</head>
               <byline>By an vncertaine Authour.</byline>
               <l>LEtters the matter done explaine;</l>
               <l>That, the words marrow doth containe,</l>
               <l>The ſight whereof quicke mindes doe gaine.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>27</hi> Vpon the death of three.</head>
               <byline>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aried three wayes: by an vncertaine Authour.</byline>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>A Bore, Snake, yong man, did one chance abide,</l>
                  <l>By ſtroke, foot, ſting, the Bore, Snake, yong man dide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>A Youth, Hog, Serpent, doth lament, fret, hiſſe,</l>
                  <l>Stung, ſtriken, bruizd, and life at once doe miſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:21"/>
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>Death at one time, a Snake, Youth, Bore doe meet,</l>
                  <l>The Bore, by wound; Youth, ſting; and Snake, by feet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>By the Tranſtatour to make it more plaeine.</head>
                  <l>A Huntſman trod an Adder that him wounded,</l>
                  <l>As he the Bore, ſo were all Three confounded.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>28</hi> Of Fortune.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Caelius Firminianus Simphoſius.</byline>
               <l>O Powerfull Chance, how changeable thou art,</l>
               <l>That ſtearnly claimſt of Rule ſo great a part!</l>
               <l>Bad men thou raiſeſt, and the Good o'rethroweſt,</l>
               <l>Keeping no credit in what thou beſtoweſt.</l>
               <l>Men vndeſeruing Fortune makes renownd,</l>
               <l>And guilteſſe perſons Fortune doth confound;</l>
               <l>The righteous Man with Pouertie ſhe grieues,</l>
               <l>And who vnworthy be, with wealth relieues;</l>
               <l>Old ſhe doth hugge, and yong men from her thruſt,</l>
               <l>The times diuiding with a will vniuſt.</l>
               <l>To th' Bad ſhe giues, what from the Good ſhe takes,</l>
               <l>And neuer iudgeth true, nor difference makes,</l>
               <l>Fraile, faithleſſe, and vnconſtant as the winde,</l>
               <l>Slippery, light, fooliſh, and like <hi>Cupid,</hi> blinde,</l>
               <l>Not euer fauouring where ſhe giues a Bleſſing,</l>
               <l>Nor whom ſhe doth forſake, for aye oppreſſing.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>29</hi> Of loue to <hi>Theotimus.</hi>
               </head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Qu. Catullus.</byline>
               <l>MY heart is fled to <hi>Theotime,</hi> I feare,</l>
               <l>As it was wont; 'tis ſo, 't has refuge there:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:21"/>What if, to ſhew the fugitiue reſpect,</l>
               <l>I had not him forbid, but to reiect?</l>
               <l>Ile goe in queſt: yet he may me deteine:</l>
               <l>What ſhould I doe? thy counſell, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> deigne.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>30</hi> Of <hi>Roſcius</hi> his beautie.</head>
               <byline>By the ſame Authour.</byline>
               <l>TO greet <hi>Aurora</hi> riſing while I chanced,</l>
               <l>Straight <hi>Roſcius</hi> at my left hand was aduanced:</l>
               <l>May I, ye Gods, by ſpeech, not loſe your loue,</l>
               <l>The ſight beneath was fairer then aboue.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>31</hi> To <hi>Phileros</hi> of loues power.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Valerius Edituus.</byline>
               <l>WHy bear'ſt thou <hi>Phileros</hi> a needleſſe light?</l>
               <l>Lets goe; my breſt with fire is fully bright;</l>
               <l>And that may vaniſh through winds raging power,</l>
               <l>Or from the Clouds a downe right ſhining ſhower</l>
               <l>But for this fire of <hi>Venus,</hi> there's no force,</l>
               <l>Except her ſelfe can quench or ſtop its courſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>32</hi> To <hi>Pamphila</hi> of an amorous extaſie.</head>
               <byline>By the ſame Authour.</byline>
               <l>WHen <hi>Pamphila,</hi> my griefe I ſeeke to breake,</l>
               <l>What I would craue of thee, I cannot ſpeake:</l>
               <l>Straight ſweats my wretched heart, then double I</l>
               <l>My prayre and power; if mute, loue-rackd I die.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="epigram">
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>33</hi> To Shepheards of Loues fire.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Porcius Licinius.</byline>
               <l>Keepers of Sheepe and of their tender Frie,</l>
               <l>Fire ſeeke ye? hither come, a Fire am I:</l>
               <l>The whole wood, if I touch it, fir'd will be,</l>
               <l>And fir'd your Cattell all, all that I ſee.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>34</hi> Vpon a Thracian Boy.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> C. Iulius Caeſar <hi>or</hi> Germanicus Auguſtus.</byline>
               <l>A <hi>Thratian</hi> Boy on <hi>Hebrus</hi> frozen playing,</l>
               <l>Broke with his weight the flood, like marble, ſtaying;</l>
               <l>And as in ſinking downe full ill he ſped,</l>
               <l>The ſlippery Teſt (alas) tooke off his head:</l>
               <l>Which when his mother found and vrn'd, quoth ſhe,</l>
               <l>For ſire, this bare I; the reſt, drown'd to be.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>35</hi> The Tombe of <hi>Lucrece.</hi>
               </head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Ouid.</byline>
               <l>IN her chaſte breſt when <hi>Lucrece</hi> ſheathd her blade,</l>
               <l>A bloody Torrent iſſuing, thus ſhe ſaid;</l>
               <l>My Spirit, before the Gods, my Blood, my Lord,</l>
               <l>Witneſſe I did not to my Shame accord:</l>
               <l>In death, for me produc'd, theyle pleade right well,</l>
               <l>Th'one ſoard to Heauen, th' other ſunke to hell.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="epigram">
               <head>36 <hi>Vpon</hi> Narciſſus.</head>
               <byline>By an vncertaine Authour.</byline>
               <l>THis is <hi>Narciſſus</hi> whom the Well did moue,</l>
               <l>To ouer-much beliefe, yet worthy Loue:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:22"/>The Banke thou ſeeſt with moiſt graſſe him doth nouriſh,</l>
               <l>That by the Spring (his Ruine) he may flouriſh.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>37</hi> Vpon three Shepheards.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Cytherius Sydonius.</byline>
               <l>A <hi>Sabine, Spartan, Laurentine,</hi> each of a diffrent roote,</l>
               <l>Did <hi>Thirſis, Theon, Almo</hi> get at high <hi>Pelorus</hi> foote,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sabine, Spartan, Laurentine,</hi> Vines, Plows, Swine did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy</l>
               <l>And <hi>Thirſis, Theon, Almo,</hi> was a ſtripling, yongſter, boy,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Thirſis, Theon, Almo</hi> then</l>
               <l>Sheepe, Kids, Goates vp did breed:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Thirſis, Theon, Almo</hi> vſd for muſicke, voice, ſtraw, reed:</l>
               <l>To <hi>Thirſis, Theon, Almo</hi> loue theſe <hi>Naīs, Niſa, Glauce</hi> ſhow'd,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Naīs, Niſa, Glauce</hi> there Lillies, Roſe, Violets beſtowd.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>38</hi> Of three Amazons fight.</head>
               <byline>By the ſame Authour.</byline>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alce, Hyppolite, Lyce</hi> (ſignall ſounded)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oehalus, Teuthras, Donis</hi> ſole confounded,</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Arcadian, Greciau, Marſian,</hi> boy, youth, peere,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Ida, Epus, Doricles</hi> full deere,</l>
               <l>With ſword, ſhaft, datt, ith'ſide, ith' guts, ith'face.</l>
               <l>On horſe, foote, charriot, and thus ends the caſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>39</hi> Of an Hermaphrodite.</head>
               <byline>By <hi>Pulex</hi> an ancient Poet.</byline>
               <l>WHile I my mothers pregnant wombe poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>To know my ſex the Gods ſhe did requeſt:</l>
               <l>A boy, quoth <hi>Sol;</hi> a girle, <hi>Mars; Iuno,</hi> neither:</l>
               <l>And being borne I was by nature either:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:23"/>Then my death queſtion'd; <hi>Iuno</hi> ſaid, By ſword:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> hang'd; <hi>Sol,</hi> drown'd: all, Fortune did afford.</l>
               <l>A tree the floud o're-ſhadowing I aſcend;</l>
               <l>My ſword and I thereon, did downwards tend:</l>
               <l>My foot ſtucke faſt, my head being ouer-waterd:</l>
               <l>Male, female, neither, I was drownd, hang'd, ſlaughter'd.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="epigram">
               <head>40 <hi>Of</hi> Acis.</head>
               <l>THe bones of <hi>Acis</hi> in this Hill repoſe,</l>
               <l>Where a ſmooth Fountaine from the bottome flowes;</l>
               <l>Signes of the <hi>Cyclops</hi> furie theſe endure,</l>
               <l>Where ſtaies thy loue, (bright Nymph) and ſorrow ſure,</l>
               <l>But ſith he periſht, he's well couer'd here,</l>
               <l>While dancing ſtreames his endleſſe name doe beare:</l>
               <l>Thus he abides whom Fame dead ſhall not ring,</l>
               <l>Whoſe cerule life glides through the liquid ſpring.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>41</hi> The Tombe of <hi>Hector.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>HEctor</hi> his countries ſhield, ſtout'ſt youth of all,</l>
               <l>That was to <hi>Troy</hi> diſtreſt another wall,</l>
               <l>Dyed by <hi>Achilles</hi> violent hand ſubdude,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Phrygian</hi> hope and ſafetie did conclude;</l>
               <l>Him 'bout thoſe walls his cruell Victor halde,</l>
               <l>Thoſe which in his youth himſelfe kept vnaſſailde.</l>
               <l>O what a ſea of griefe did that day bring,</l>
               <l>To his wife, mother, and the good old king?</l>
               <l>But his vnhappy Father bought for gold,</l>
               <l>And wailing laid him in this earthly mold.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="epigram">
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>42</hi> The Tombe of <hi>Achilles.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Chilles, Thetis</hi> ſonne am I well knowne,</l>
               <l>Through valiant Acts and proweſſe famous growne,</l>
               <l>I that ſo oft ore threw my foes in fight,</l>
               <l>And ſingly many thouſands put to flight:</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Hectors</hi> fall my glory higheſt raiſd,</l>
               <l>That many a time the <hi>Grecian</hi> powers craz'd;</l>
               <l>For which, by ſlaying him, reuenge I reap'd,</l>
               <l>And then my ſword on <hi>Troye</hi> confuſion heap'd:</l>
               <l>At length by trechery queld on hoſtile ground,</l>
               <l>Aboue the ſtarres a conquerour I was cround.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poems">
            <head>The praiſes of <hi>Virgil,</hi> and his workes.</head>
            <div n="1" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>1 Virgil</hi> of himſelfe.</head>
               <l>SVch <hi>Romans</hi> as ſweet <hi>Homer</hi> haue not read,</l>
               <l>By reading me, may be of either ſped:</l>
               <l>His fields <hi>Greece</hi> doth admire, ſo large and fild,</l>
               <l>But leſſe our ground appeares, yet fitly tild.</l>
               <l>The ſhepheard, plowman, ſouldier heres for thee;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Greeks</hi> haue each but one, I haue all three.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="poem">
               <head>2 <hi>Of</hi> Virgil.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Alcinous.</byline>
               <l>IF <hi>Homer</hi> for no Poet you allow,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Maro</hi> ſhall be Firſt, the Second now.</l>
               <l>But from the Poets if you <hi>Maro</hi> ſeuer,</l>
               <l>Farre from the Firſt the Seond ſhall be euer.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>3</hi> Of Virgils Aeneids.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Cornelius Gallus.</byline>
               <l>LEt vs (great <hi>Caeſar</hi>) in mirths time be ſad,</l>
               <l>For onely <hi>Virgils</hi> loſſe, whom I lament.</l>
               <l>But he his <hi>Aeneid</hi> to be read forbad,</l>
               <l>Which muſt be ſo, if thou but giue conſent.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome,</hi> yea the world to thee their prayers turne,</l>
               <l>From fire to ſaue ſo many Captaines ſtories.</l>
               <l>Shall <hi>Troy</hi> againe with flames, (yet greater) burne?</l>
               <l>O make thy deeds read with <hi>Italians</hi> glories,</l>
               <l>And ſee him by a greater <hi>Nuncius</hi> deckt,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Caeſars</hi> mouth can more then Fates effect.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>4</hi> The Edict of <hi>Octauius Caeſar</hi> for the preſeruation of the Aeneid.</head>
               <l>COuld then a voice peruerſe that ſtraight expirde,</l>
               <l>Will a miſdeed ſo dire? ſhalt then be firde?</l>
               <l>Shall learned <hi>Maro</hi>'s noble Muſe depart,</l>
               <l>(Ah worthleſſe ill) and loſt be wealthy Art?</l>
               <l>And can theſe eyes behold it? nor the flame</l>
               <l>His Honour ſpare, or ſaue lines worthy fame?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebus</hi> forbid it, and the Siſters nine:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ceres</hi> preuent it, and the God of Wine.</l>
               <l>In armes he was your Souldier, whoſe Pen ſought;</l>
               <l>Your husbandman ith' countrey, for he taught,</l>
               <l>What vertues be in Summer and the Spring,</l>
               <l>What good doth Autumne and the Winter bring,</l>
               <l>New form'd the Fields, the Vine and Elme combin'd.</l>
               <l>Kept Sheepe, and vnto Bees their Hiue aſſign'd.</l>
               <l>Now theſe (if it be lawfull ſo to ſay)</l>
               <l>Did he deliuer to be caſt away?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:24"/>But Lawes faith ſhould be kept, the deads mans will,</l>
               <l>What ere it bids be done, we muſt fulfill.</l>
               <l>Yet rather let vs burſt lawes reuerend power,</l>
               <l>Then ſee one day ſo many lines deuoure,</l>
               <l>So many lines congeſted day and night,</l>
               <l>Or dying words deſtroy his watching quite.</l>
               <l>If at his end prowd griefe this Errour wrought,</l>
               <l>If (witleſſe what) he ſpake with wauering thought,</l>
               <l>Not willing, but compeld by pangs o'reſpent;</l>
               <l>Or his minde blinde through loathſome languiſhment:</l>
               <l>Shall therefore <hi>Troy</hi> be forc'd to view againe</l>
               <l>Her flaming Ruine, and a new complaine?</l>
               <l>Shall wretched <hi>Dido</hi>'s wounds with fire be wounded?</l>
               <l>And ſhall a worke ſo ſacred be confounded?</l>
               <l>And one miſchieuous houre, with trecherous Error,</l>
               <l>To aſhes turne ſo many fields of Terror?</l>
               <l>Come, ye ſweet Muſes, from your <hi>Syluan</hi> caues,</l>
               <l>And quench theſe burning fires with flowing waues;</l>
               <l>And leſt a Poets Muſe being ſo renown'd,</l>
               <l>Should come to ruine, let the flame be drown'd.</l>
               <l>Famous ith' world, yet to himſelfe ingrate,</l>
               <l>May <hi>Maro</hi> liue, his charge ſo obſtinate</l>
               <l>Let vs controwle: In death he's ſatiſfide,</l>
               <l>So ſhall his Verſe eternally abide,</l>
               <l>The Muſes all reſounding, and his name,</l>
               <l>Crown'd with a deitie all Rome proclaime.</l>
               <l>May he be praiſd and honour'd, may he pleaſe,</l>
               <l>Flouriſh, be often read, loue ioyn'd with theſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Other Copies are thus.</head>
               <l>COme, Muſes, and vſe all your waters here,</l>
               <l>To quench the fire, liue <hi>Maro</hi> euery-where.</l>
               <l>What he to th' whole world enuious (as ingrate)</l>
               <l>Both of himſelfe and workes and after-Fate.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:25"/>Growne hurtfull, had commanded, be't our part</l>
               <l>To countermand; being dead, he's pleaſd in heart.</l>
               <l>Yea rather let the Muſes all reſound</l>
               <l>His verſe eternall, and his name renown'd,</l>
               <l>The people deifie, fade let him neuer,</l>
               <l>Still be peruſde, delight, affected euer.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>5</hi> Of <hi>Virgils</hi> Aeneid preſerued.</head>
               <byline>By <hi>Sulpitius</hi> of Carthage.</byline>
               <l>THat greedy fire this volume ſhould conſume,</l>
               <l>Which ſets <hi>Aeneas</hi> forth, t'was <hi>Virgils</hi> doome:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tucca</hi> and <hi>Varius</hi> nill, nor thou permit,</l>
               <l>(Great <hi>Caeſar</hi>) and ſo ſau'dſt the <hi>Latian</hi> writ.</l>
               <l>Vnhappy <hi>Troy</hi> was like agen to fall,</l>
               <l>And with a ſecond fire to periſh all.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>6</hi> In praiſe of the Aeneid.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Ouid.</byline>
               <l>WAndring <hi>Aeneas</hi> lofty <hi>Romes</hi> beginning,</l>
               <l>No worke hath <hi>Italy</hi> more glory winning.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>7</hi> Of <hi>Virgils</hi> want on writing.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Ouid <hi>to</hi> Auguſtus.</byline>
               <l>YEt happy he, whoſe Muſe thy <hi>Aeneid</hi> bred,</l>
               <l>Armes and a man brought to a <hi>Tyrian</hi> bed,</l>
               <l>Yea in verſe <hi>Bucolicke,</hi> before but yong,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phyllis</hi> and <hi>Amarillys</hi> loues he ſung.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="poem">
               <head>8 <hi>Of</hi> Virgil.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Chriſtodorus.</byline>
               <l>ANd, whom for Eloquence <hi>Auſonia</hi> choſe</l>
               <l>Her fauourite, ſweet Swan-like <hi>Maro</hi> flouriſht,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:25"/>Whom with renowne at <hi>Rome</hi> where <hi>Tyber</hi> flowes,</l>
               <l>His country, as another <hi>Homer,</hi> nouriſht.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>9</hi> Vpon <hi>Virgil</hi> and his workes.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Sextus Propertius <hi>in his</hi> 2. <hi>Booke, Elegy</hi> 24.</byline>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>PHoebus</hi>-fenc'd <hi>Actium, Virgd</hi> it delights,</l>
                  <l>That he could ſing, with <hi>Caeſars</hi> nauall fights.</l>
                  <l>Who, with <hi>Aeneas</hi> conflicts, now reſtores</l>
                  <l>The citie ruin'd on <hi>Lauinian</hi> ſhores.</l>
                  <l>Ye <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> writers backwards ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Some greater worke then th'lliad is in hand.</l>
                  <l>Thou by <hi>Galeſus,</hi> where Pines ſhading breed,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thyrſis</hi> and <hi>Daphnis</hi> ſingſt with ſlender Reed:</l>
                  <l>And how Ten apples could a Maid infect,</l>
                  <l>And from the printed Teat a Kid ſelect.</l>
                  <l>He's bleſt that buyes loue at ſo deare a Rate,</l>
                  <l>Though <hi>Tityrus</hi> doe ſing to her ingrate:</l>
                  <l>Bleſt <hi>Corydon</hi> that tempts <hi>Alexis</hi> chaſte,</l>
                  <l>The Husbandman his Lords delights to taſte:</l>
                  <l>Though wearied with his pipe to reſt he layes him,</l>
                  <l>The gentle <hi>Hamadryades</hi> doe praiſe him.</l>
                  <l>The precepts of old <hi>Heſiod</hi> thou doſt ſing,</l>
                  <l>What field yeelds corne, what vallyes grapes doe bring.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Phoebus</hi> if the learned Lute he take</l>
                  <l>And play thereon, ſuch Muſicke thou doſt make.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:26"/>
               <p>Here may I conclude his praiſes with two lines</p>
               <l>vpon his <hi>Georgickes,</hi> written by our moſt witty</l>
               <l>and famous Epigrammatiſt, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Owen,</hi> late</l>
               <l>Fellow of New-Colledge in Oxford de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus Engliſhed.</hi>
               </l>
               <lg>
                  <l>TRim verſes of Grounds Tillage, <hi>Maro</hi> writ,</l>
                  <l>Who thereby tills the Readers fields and wit.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="epitaphs">
               <head>Epitaphs vpon Virgil.</head>
               <byline>By diuers illuſtrious perſons.</byline>
               <div n="1" type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>1</hi> Palladius.</head>
                  <l>HEre am I couer'd, whoſe late ruſticke pen,</l>
                  <l>Through woods and fields came to the armes of men.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2</hi> Aſclepiades.</head>
                  <l>I <hi>Maro</hi> ſung of <hi>Mars,</hi> a man, ſheepe, corne:</l>
                  <l>Buried in <hi>Naples,</hi> but in <hi>Mantua</hi> borne.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>3</hi> Euſebius.</head>
                  <l>Here <hi>Virgil</hi> lies, that paſtures did reherſe,</l>
                  <l>Good husbandry and <hi>Troian</hi> warres in verſe.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>4</hi> Pompelianus.</head>
                  <l>The Poet that ſung battailes, fields and ſheepe,</l>
                  <l>Dy'd in <hi>Calabria,</hi> and here lies aſleepe.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>5</hi> Maximianus.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virgil</hi> by Verſe, of cattell, grounds, and warres,</l>
                  <l>Hath merited fame laſting like the ſtarres.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>6</hi> Vitalis.</head>
                  <l>My verſes, woods, grounds, warres; my place of birth,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mantua;</hi> name, <hi>Virgil;</hi> my graue, <hi>Naples</hi> earth.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>7</hi> Baſilius.</head>
                  <l>Vnder this heape the Poet <hi>Maro</hi> lies,</l>
                  <l>That woods, fields, warres, in verſes beautifies.</l>
               </div>
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:26"/>
               <div n="8" type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>8</hi> Aſmodianus.</head>
                  <l>The Shepheards Poet here vntimely preſt,</l>
                  <l>Country and combats I in verſe expreſt.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>9</hi> Vouianus.</head>
                  <l>Here lies wit-honour'd <hi>Maro,</hi> whoſe Muſe came</l>
                  <l>From woods to fields, from fields to <hi>Mars</hi> his game.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>10</hi> Eugenius.</head>
                  <l>Precepts I writ of Paſturage and tyllage,</l>
                  <l>Then Armies, vntill Death of me made pillage.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>11</hi> Iulianus.</head>
                  <l>Here ſleepeth <hi>Virgil,</hi> that in ſweeteſt meaſures</l>
                  <l>Vtter'd <hi>Pan, Ceres,</hi> and <hi>Bellona</hi>'s pleaſures.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>12</hi> Hilaſius.</head>
                  <l>Shepheards and Plowmens cunning I that taught,</l>
                  <l>And ſet forth fights, this Tombe am vnder brought.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="epitaph">
                  <head>The ſame Authour vpon <hi>Virgils</hi> picture.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maro,</hi> thy Picture foyles the fatall dart,</l>
                  <l>Whom Nature tooke, we ſee reſtor'd by Art.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epitaph">
                  <head>Another by the ſame Authour.</head>
                  <l>So great a Poet feeles no hurt by death,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Verſes honour keepes him ſtill in breath.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Virgil,</hi> or another in his name.</head>
                  <l>Me <hi>Mantua, Brunduſe, Naples,</hi> bore, tooke, holds,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe volume, paſtures, plow-lands, armes, infolds.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Vpon his Daphnis.</head>
               <byline>By an vncertaine Authour.</byline>
               <l>In <hi>Daphnis</hi> wailing for thy <hi>Flaccus</hi> fate,</l>
               <l>With Gods, learn'd <hi>Maro,</hi> thou mak'ſt him a mate.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <byline>By an vncertaine Authour.</byline>
               <l>I Shepheard, Plowman, Horſeman ſtout, did</l>
               <l>Paſture, my Goats, with leaues,</l>
               <l>till, my grounds, with ſpade,</l>
               <l>out-ſtand, my enemies, with hand.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="epigram">
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:27"/>
               <p>Now ſeeing I haue before inſerted an Epigram made by M. <hi>Iohn Owen,</hi> giue me leaue in this place to annex his owne Epitaph, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen in a plate of Braſſe, and fixed vnder his monumentall Image, formed and erected by the moſt exquiſite Artiſt, M. <hi>Epiphanius Eueſham,</hi> withinthe Cathedrall Church of Saint <hi>Paul, thus Engliſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>SMall was thy ſtate and ſtature, which doe claime</l>
                  <l>Small ſtatue, through great lands thy ſmall Booke flies,</l>
                  <l>But ſmall thine honour is not, nor thy fame,</l>
                  <l>For greater wit then thine the world denies:</l>
                  <l>Whom a ſmall houſe, a great Church ſhelter giues,</l>
                  <l>A Poet when he dies then truly liues.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poems">
            <head>The Arguments of <hi>Virgils</hi> workes. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Monoſtichs of all his workes.</head>
               <l>He ſings in ſundry ſtrifes the Shepheards Muſe,</l>
               <l>Grounds tillage learnedly he ſhewes in meaſures,</l>
               <l>Teacheth to graft and plant without abuſe.</l>
               <l>Beaſts nurture next, and <hi>Pales</hi> with her treaſures.</l>
               <l>Bees ordring then with honies gifts and pleaſures.</l>
               <l>To <hi>Carthage</hi> comes <hi>Aeneas</hi> wandring farre,</l>
               <l>Reports the manner of the <hi>Troian</hi> warre.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:27"/>The ſame Reporter ſhewes his proper courſes:</l>
               <l>Death on her ſelfe loue-burnt <hi>Eliza</hi> forces.</l>
               <l>His fathers graue with ſports <hi>Aeneas</hi> graces:</l>
               <l>Then Ghoſts he viſits and infernall places.</l>
               <l>He enters <hi>Latium</hi> and th' <hi>Italian</hi> bounds.</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Turnus</hi> from his roofe warre-thundring ſounds.</l>
               <l>A mother and young men her ſonne lament,</l>
               <l>To death is <hi>Lauſus</hi> and his father ſent,</l>
               <l>Reneng'd <hi>Camilla</hi> by a ſpeare extinct,</l>
               <l>With ſpirts infernall <hi>Daunus</hi> ſonne is linkt.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>2</hi> Tetraſtichs of his <hi>4.</hi> Bookes of Georgickes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHat man in <hi>Bucolicks,</hi> and read how well</l>
                  <l>In tillage and in vines, trees, plants, heards, bees,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Troyes</hi> Poet was, <hi>Tetraſtichs</hi> here ſhall tell:</l>
                  <l>Each bookes contents, who viewes my writing, ſees.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>What makes Corne thriue he ſhewes, what wether's meet</l>
                  <l>For Husbandmen the fields with ploughes to greet.</l>
                  <l>How, caſting ſeeds, he ſhould manure the ſoyle,</l>
                  <l>To reape much profit for his coſt and toyle.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>Earths tillage hitherto and ſeaſon-skill,</l>
                  <l>Now fings he vine-leaues and the virent hill:</l>
                  <l>What places <hi>Bacchus</hi> and the vineyard ſute,</l>
                  <l>And th' Oliue branch that beares the chiefeſt fruite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pales</hi> and Shepheards through the world renowu'd,</l>
                  <l>Ordring of cattell and graſſe clothed ground,</l>
                  <l>What ſoile to beaſts or lambes we ſhould aſſigne,</l>
                  <l>All theſe our Poet ſhewes in verſe diuine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:28"/>
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>Then Realmes of dew-bred hony ſweetly ſmelling,</l>
                  <l>Bees bred in <hi>Hybla</hi> and their waxen dwelling,</l>
                  <l>What flowres they ſucke, with ſwarme collecting drifts,</l>
                  <l>He ſhewes, and their moiſt combe, celeſtiall gifts.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Monoſtichs of his <hi>12.</hi> Bookes of Aeneids.</head>
               <l>I Th' firſt, <hi>Aeneas</hi> comes to th' <hi>Lybian</hi> Queene:</l>
               <l>Ith' ſecond, be <hi>Troyes</hi> warres and ruine ſeene.</l>
               <l>The third, his wandring ſhewes, and buried ſire:</l>
               <l>The fourth, <hi>Eliza</hi> vext with <hi>Cupids</hi> fire.</l>
               <l>Games in the fifth, and burning Ships appeare:</l>
               <l>Hell, in the ſixth, is ſearch'd, and Spirits there.</l>
               <l>To th' deſtin'd land the ſeuenth <hi>Aeneas</hi> brings.</l>
               <l>Warres preparation th' eighth 'gainſt foemen fings.</l>
               <l>They fight ith' ninth, whoſe Captaine is remote.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mezentius</hi> flies ith' tenth to <hi>Charons</hi> boate</l>
               <l>Ith' laſt but one, hard <hi>Mars</hi> a virgin ſpild,</l>
               <l>Ith' laſt, by armes diuine is <hi>Turnus</hi> kild.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Pentestichs of the ſame.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>AT <hi>Iuno</hi>'s ſuite winds <hi>Aeole</hi> ſetting free,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Affricke</hi> driues the <hi>Troians</hi> wandring fleet;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioues</hi> words to <hi>Venus</hi> grieu'd a comfort be,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dido</hi> in <hi>Carthoge</hi> doth <hi>Aeneas</hi> meet,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid, Iulus</hi> like her heart doth greet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeneas</hi> mou'd warres, fortune doth relate,</l>
                  <l>The horſe, how guilefull <hi>Greekes</hi> with <hi>Sinon</hi> were.</l>
                  <l>The citie ruin'd <hi>Priams</hi> wretched fate,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19902:28"/>How on his ſhoulders he through fire did beare</l>
                  <l>His father, and did loſe <hi>Creuſa</hi> deare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Troy</hi> falne, with ſhips <hi>Aeneas</hi> runs his race,</l>
                  <l>And a new citie doth in <hi>Thrace</hi> beſtow,</l>
                  <l>Whence vrg'd, in <hi>Creet</hi> another he doth place,</l>
                  <l>Then dangers from <hi>Helenus</hi> he doth know,</l>
                  <l>Flies the blinde <hi>Cyclops,</hi> layes his father low.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dido,</hi> whom <hi>Anne</hi> perſwadeth, <hi>Cupid</hi> fireth,</l>
                  <l>She in a caue ſtorme-forc'd her luſts fulfills,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iarbas Iupiter</hi> with praiers tireth,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeneas</hi> puts to Sea, as <hi>Joue</hi> him wills,</l>
                  <l>She rack'd with griefe and loue her life-bloud ſpills.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>Fortune to <hi>Sicily</hi> him brings againe,</l>
                  <l>Who to his fathers tombe great honour payes;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iris</hi> by fire begins his Nauies bane,</l>
                  <l>There Mates he leaues, ſad <hi>Venus</hi> prayer allayes</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neptune,</hi> where ſleepe ends <hi>Palinurus</hi> dayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>The <hi>Phrygian</hi> treads in ſacred <hi>Cumae</hi>-towne,</l>
                  <l>Deſires an anſwer from the Propheteſſe,</l>
                  <l>Inhumes <hi>Miſenus,</hi> to Dis then goes downe,</l>
                  <l>His offpring there <hi>Anchiſes</hi> doth expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>And how thenceforth to conquer all diſtreſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>Ith' end the <hi>Troians</hi> doe <hi>Laurentum</hi> ſee,</l>
                  <l>Glad of peace granted, build in citie wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Forth <hi>Iuno</hi> calls a night-borne Furie, ſhe</l>
                  <l>Makes warre betwixt them, and the <hi>Latines</hi> riſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turnus</hi> with aide ſtraight <hi>Italy</hi> ſupplies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>Violent warres <hi>Aeneas</hi> notes in hand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Euander</hi> wins to helpe him in the field,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19902:29"/>And to his troops gaines all <hi>Hetruria</hi> land,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> craues armes which <hi>Mulciber</hi> doth yeeld,</l>
                  <l>With ſtout acts of his iſſue in a ſhield.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iris</hi> from <hi>Iuno</hi> vnto <hi>Turnus</hi> haſteth,</l>
                  <l>Rouzeth his heart, his Troopes he doth not ſtay:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Troians</hi> be beſieg'd, their Ships fire waſteth.</l>
                  <l>Two friends for night-warre their liues dearely pay;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turnus</hi> the Tents doth win, is driuen away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioue</hi> calmes his wiues and daughters brawling ſpight,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Troian</hi> Worthy, fraught with ayde, arriues;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rutilians</hi> meet them, at tho ſhore they fight:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turnus</hi> kills <hi>Pallas,</hi> out <hi>Aeneas</hi> driues</l>
                  <l>(Loſing the victor prowd) for one, two liues.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>Due honour to the dead both parts commend,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diomed</hi> helpe to th' <hi>Latines</hi> doth deny,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turnus</hi> in words with <hi>Drance</hi> doth contend:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeneas</hi> horſe fore-ſends, by th' way they trie</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Camilla</hi>'s might; ſhe flaine, her ſouldiers flie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turnus</hi> to contract with <hi>Aeneas</hi> grew,</l>
                  <l>That, the <hi>Rutilians</hi> breake; faire <hi>Venus</hi> cures</l>
                  <l>Her ſonne, thoſe queld their periur'd action rue.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turnus</hi> perforce <hi>Aeneas</hi> force endures;</l>
                  <l>And his owne death by <hi>Pallas</hi> belt procures.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Of the Supply or addition to the twelue Bookes of the Aeneids.</head>
               <byline>
                  <hi>Written by</hi> Maphaeus Vegius.</byline>
               <l>
                  <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rnus</hi> through fight no ſooner leaues to liue,</l>
               <l>But his to th' Victor ſtoop e <hi>Troy</hi>-troops attending:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:29"/>Then worthy honour to the Gods they giue,</l>
               <l>To ioy, Sire, Sonne, and fellow-Souldiers bending,</l>
               <l>Mindfull of perils paſt; for <hi>Turnus,</hi> moane</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Latinus</hi> makes; his deare Sonnes funerall,</l>
               <l>And wretched Country by fire ouerthrowne,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Daunus</hi> laments: In mariage after all,</l>
               <l>And mirthfull <hi>Hymens</hi> bonds the king combines</l>
               <l>His daughter with <hi>Aeneae;</hi> either nation</l>
               <l>Triumphs ith' league of peace; then he aſſignes</l>
               <l>Vnto a citie his wifes appellation.</l>
               <l>And laſtly, while he reignes in pleaſing reſt,</l>
               <l>With heau'ns ioyes is by his mother bleſt.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>5</hi> Decaſtichs of the <hi>12.</hi> Books of the Aeneids, by <hi>Ouid.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AS much as <hi>Virgil</hi> to rich <hi>Homer</hi> gaue,</l>
                  <l>So much from <hi>Ouid</hi> ſhall his <hi>Virgil</hi> haue.</l>
                  <l>My ſelfe to ſet before thee neuer bent,</l>
                  <l>In wit to follow thee I reſt content.</l>
                  <l>Thy Bookes chiefe Arguments I here vnfold,</l>
                  <l>Leſt any Ignorant ſhould errour hold.</l>
                  <l>Ten verſes of each one I haue compoſde,</l>
                  <l>Where the whole Aeneid they may view encloſde:</l>
                  <l>Affirming on my credit, that I make</l>
                  <l>Theſe Titles not a line for Enuies ſake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <l>Warre-fam'd <hi>Aeneas,</hi> with the beſt a Mate</l>
                  <l>In Goodneſſe, preſt by partiall <hi>Juno</hi>'s hate,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Italy</hi> on <hi>Sicile</hi>-billowes bound,</l>
                  <l>Storme-driuen came at length to <hi>Lybian</hi> ground.</l>
                  <l>And, with his friend vnwitting where they were,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Vonus</hi> learn'd that <hi>Dido</hi> reigned there;</l>
                  <l>Who, in a cloud her citie entring, found</l>
                  <l>His waue-depriu'd Aſſociates ſafe and ſound.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19902:30"/>And to the Queene moſt welcome, doth prepare</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Troys</hi> downfall at her bidding to declare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <l>All being ſilent, this heroicke wight</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Troy</hi> and his the fortunes doth recite,</l>
                  <l>The trecherous <hi>Greekes, Minerua</hi>'s feigned gifts,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Laocons</hi> paine and <hi>Sinons</hi> cunning ſhifts:</l>
                  <l>How he himſelfe was warn'd by <hi>Hector</hi> ſleeping,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Troy</hi> next in flames, his country ruin'd, weeping.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Priams</hi> euer-lamentable wrecke;</l>
                  <l>By hand <hi>Aſcanius</hi> taken, on his necke</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Anchiſes,</hi> but by fate <hi>Creuſa</hi> reau'd</l>
                  <l>In following, on the mount his mates receau'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <l>How after <hi>Troy</hi> deſtroyd he left the place,</l>
                  <l>And with a nauie firſt arriu'd at <hi>Thrace;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Founded a citie, how the king did take</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Polydores</hi> life, and what <hi>Apollo</hi> ſpake,</l>
                  <l>His voyage into <hi>Crete,</hi> thence call'd to Seas,</l>
                  <l>By new fates driuen to the <hi>Strophades.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The charge of foule <hi>Celeno, Harpies</hi> flight,</l>
                  <l>How he <hi>Helenus</hi> left that warn'd him right:</l>
                  <l>Freed <hi>Achemenides</hi> from <hi>Cyclops</hi> awe,</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Drepanùm</hi> interr'd his father ſaw.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4</head>
                  <l>But now Loues grieuo us fire the Queene hath ſeiz'd,</l>
                  <l>Who, by her ſiſter led, to yeeld is pleaſd,</l>
                  <l>The Gods with gifts they loade and ſacrifice.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> a ſecret league in hunting ties.</l>
                  <l>It ſpreds abroad; for flight <hi>Aeneas</hi> then</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Ioue</hi> enioyn'd, prepares both ſhips and men;</l>
                  <l>Which amorous <hi>Dido</hi> finding, wooes their ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Yet not preuailing where fates call away,</l>
                  <l>A wood-fire built aſcends, and ſpeakes her laſt,</l>
                  <l>Then wounded ſote, her life awaydoth caſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:30"/>
                  <head>5</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeneas</hi> borne to <hi>Sicily,</hi> the Ghoſt</l>
                  <l>Of dead <hi>Anchiſes</hi> celebrates, his Oaſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Acetes</hi> with him orders Games for prize,</l>
                  <l>A Shaft, to all prodigious, burning flies;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iris</hi> in old wiues habit <hi>Beroe</hi> ſeemes,</l>
                  <l>His nauie fires, that ſudden raine redeemes.</l>
                  <l>In ſleepe his father ſhewes warres to betide him,</l>
                  <l>And to the court of <hi>Pluto</hi> who ſhall guide him:</l>
                  <l>Fight-flying men and matrons left intown'd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeneas</hi> mournes for <hi>Palinurus</hi> drownd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6</head>
                  <l>With <hi>Sybils</hi> anſwer he from <hi>Cumae</hi> came,</l>
                  <l>Buryed <hi>Miſenus,</hi> gaue a hill the name.</l>
                  <l>The Branch he plucks the gods appeaſd, he venters,</l>
                  <l>And with th'old Propheteſſe hells Entrie enters,</l>
                  <l>Knowes <hi>Palinurus,</hi> comforts <hi>Dido</hi> there,</l>
                  <l>Much wounded then <hi>Deiphobus</hi> doth appeare;</l>
                  <l>Learnes the Ghoſts penance from <hi>Sybilla</hi>'s tale,</l>
                  <l>And meets <hi>Anchiſes</hi> in a virent vale,</l>
                  <l>Who ſhewes to him his Progenies eſtates,</l>
                  <l>Which done, from thence returnes he to his mates.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7</head>
                  <l>His Nurſe he buries, and to Sea he goes,</l>
                  <l>Comes to <hi>Laurentum,</hi> this the Land he knowes,</l>
                  <l>By his ſonnes ſpeeches, deſtin'd: Looke, ſaith he,</l>
                  <l>We feed from Tables; By lot choſen be</l>
                  <l>A hundred Orators, who ſent to craue</l>
                  <l>The kings good will, that, with his daughter haue.</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>Iuno</hi>'s wrath <hi>Alecto</hi> breakes the twiſt,</l>
                  <l>In words they iarre, though pious Fates reſiſt.</l>
                  <l>A heart <hi>Aſcanius</hi> wounds, which warre begets,</l>
                  <l>Nations prepare to ioyne, youth fighting frets.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19902:31"/>
                  <head>8</head>
                  <l>From <hi>Laurent</hi> caſtle <hi>Turnus</hi> warre dorh ſpred,</l>
                  <l>And greets by <hi>Venulus</hi> great <hi>Diomed:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who ayd requires, and ſhe wes a reaſon why,</l>
                  <l>To king <hi>Euander</hi> fled from <hi>Arcady,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That new realme ſeekes, God warn'd <hi>Aeneas</hi> goes,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſonne and troopes he gaines to his diſpoſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pallas</hi> ill-fated him conſorts to fighting,</l>
                  <l>Who ſtrengthned now in's mothers gifts delighting</l>
                  <l>Ith' ſhield, where Captaines fates and fortunes ſhine,</l>
                  <l>And of his offpring, notes the worke diuine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9</head>
                  <l>And while theſe things wete done on either ſide,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turnus</hi> from <hi>Inno</hi> warn'd to battaile, hy'd.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Troians</hi> ſhips, which his dart fire to burne,</l>
                  <l>To forme of Sea-Nymphs doth <hi>Ioues</hi> power turne.</l>
                  <l>Ill ſpeeds th'attempt of <hi>Niſus</hi> and his friend:</l>
                  <l>They fight, the <hi>Troians,</hi> Tents and Vale defend.</l>
                  <l>Bold <hi>Remulus</hi> by faire <hi>Iulus</hi> fell.</l>
                  <l>Way's forc'd, two brothers <hi>Turnus</hi> turnes to hell.</l>
                  <l>Yea many a <hi>Troian</hi> by his hand expires,</l>
                  <l>Then to his owne pauillions tyr'd retires.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioue</hi> touching theſe affaires a Councell calls,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turnus</hi> his part meane time begirt the walls.</l>
                  <l>Noble <hi>Aeneas</hi> many a thouſand brings.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mars</hi> calls, and th' aire with all their forces rings,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pallas</hi> drops downe at mighty <hi>Turnus</hi> feet,</l>
                  <l>Captaines and people nameleſſe death doe meet.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iuno</hi> drawes <hi>Turnus</hi> from theſe martiall bands,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mezentius</hi> reſcude, ſtiffe <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſtands,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe conquering hand ends <hi>Lauſus:</hi> and that deed,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mezentius,</hi> to reuenge, as ill doth ſpeed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11</head>
                  <l>To <hi>Mars, Aeneas</hi> yeelds a Trophy wonne,</l>
                  <l>And to <hi>Euander</hi> ſends his ſlaughter'd ſonne:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19902:31"/>Then giues the <hi>Latines</hi> funerall right and ſpace,</l>
                  <l>A fathers loue <hi>Euander</hi> ſhewes in place;</l>
                  <l>The dead diuided they prepare for vrnes;</l>
                  <l>With armes-denyall <hi>Venulus</hi> returnes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Drances</hi> and <hi>Turnus</hi> (peace <hi>Latinus</hi> crying)</l>
                  <l>Each other taunt; in wait <hi>Aeneas</hi> lying.</l>
                  <l>More warres; the <hi>Troians</hi> win, <hi>Camilla</hi> ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>All threaten till each part their Tents attaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12</head>
                  <l>Now <hi>Turnus,</hi> with croſſe warres the <hi>Latines</hi> tyr'd,</l>
                  <l>Will ſingle fight, peace by the king defir'd,</l>
                  <l>His part muſt yeeld thats conquer'd, they conclude,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iuturna, Turnus</hi> ſiſter doth delude,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Camertes</hi> turn'd, and moues the troopes to fight,</l>
                  <l>One ſtayes <hi>Aeneas</hi> with an arrowes flight:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe care his ſonne preſerues, the Towne he takes:</l>
                  <l>Hanging her ſelfe loath'd life the Queene forſakes:</l>
                  <l>With Troops the Champions fenc'd, in Martiall ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeneas</hi> takes from <hi>Turnus</hi> armes and life.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:19902:32"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
